(GROANlNG)
Three letters, people, will get you
a hot cup of coffee and a warm blanket.
What do you say, Class 5506?
CADETS: Oorah.
BEN: This is an oxygen-deprivation
anaerobic exercise.
You and your partner
will push your brick
along the bottom of the pool,
down and back.
If you need air, you may surface.
One breath.
Your partner must remain underwater
until you return.
Your brick can only move
while both of you are touching it.
If you both surface, you both fail.
This exercise is designed
to teach you teamwork.
On my whistle, drop your gear,
enter the pool and pair up.
I said one breath, Sunkist. Let's go!
-I can't.
-Come on!
-"l can't."
Get your ass out of the pool! Let's go!
Come on! Lean and rest.
You wanna quit, just quit now.
I could use those new shoes.
Senior Chief, we got a problem.
Somebody's missing.
Jesus Christ.
That's gotta be a new record. Oorah.
I'm so sick of records. Go get him.
You think I'm impressed because
you can hold your breath, Goldfish?
I wouldn't venture to say
what would impress you, Senior Chief.
All right. Get him out of the pool.
We're done for the day.
Out of the pool, Fischer. Let's move.
-Oorah!
-Move your ass.
Pop tall, Sunkist.
INSTRUCTOR: Out of the pool.
Out of the pool.
Records.
Never stare
directly into the flame, people.
It will impair your night vision.
SKlNNER: This is a Mark 58 flare.
This is what it looks like.
It'll light up a 50-foot swath of water
and can be detected by infrared
miles out.
This is a demonstration model.
The normal one will burn
for 40 to 60 minutes.
INSTRUCTOR: Hey, pay attention.
The Mark 58 is used to reference
the wind, to detect a current.
Petty Officer Watson is gonna talk
a little bit more about that.
(ECHOING)
Five minutes.
WATSON: The vessel you're looking
at right now,
people, is listing to the port side.
As a rescue swimmer, when you get
to the door of the helicopter,
you need to look down
and pay attention
to what you really have down there.
It's very important
that you understand your limitations.
Limitations without understanding
are gonna get you killed.
Case in point, this vessel's trapped
in pancake ice in the Bering Sea.
And as you can see,
the crew are out on the deck
in a relatively manageable
hoisting position.
But suddenly...
Those pieces of ice can weigh in
upwards of thousands of pounds.
Now imagine yourself trapped
in between 2,000-pound pieces of ice
trying to free-swim.
Thank you, Chief.
Next scenario, Petty Officer Watson.
WATSON: Before you leave
that helicopter, going down to a...
Standardization is one of the reasons
we were so successful during Katrina.
We had crews come in
from all over the country,
but it didn't matter, because we have
all been trained the same way.
I didn't know my pilot,
I didn't know my copilot,
I didn't know my flight mechanic.
But guess what?
It didn't matter, because...
That's why we do it.
So you have to get your mind
wrapped around that idea.
When that helicopter starts going,
when the wind starts coming...
CADETS: Twenty!
HALL: Down! Up!
-Twenty-one!
-Down! Up!
-Twenty-two!
Twenty-three!
-Two!
-Down!
-Up!
-Three!
(CADETS CHANTlNG)
Don't need no land
Don't need no tree
Out in the water
That's where I wanna be
(SHeDAISY PLA YING
SOMETHlNG TO TALK ABOUT)
-Hey, Mags, can I have a beer?
-MAGGlE: Sure.
Well, well.
So you are gonna
have a drink with me.
No, I'm having a drink near you.
Entirely different thing.
You're a regular lightning rod,
aren't you?
-What's your name?
-Daisy Buchanan.
You're lying, Daisy Buchanan.
-There is that possibility.
-No.
That was a sure-fire lie.
So I take it
you've read The Great Gatsby.
-Where's my money?
-It's not on me.
But it is close. In a very safe place.
Now, I've drawn a map
with a complex set of clues.
Each one is more fiendishly clever
than the last.
That works, too.
This is just a picture of your pants.
Yeah, but it's a bad picture, which is
what makes it so fiendishly clever.
Nice.
How did Emily Thomas
become a schoolteacher?
Well, how does Jake Fischer
become a guy
who wants to jump out of helicopters?
I killed a couple guys
and had to get out of Dodge.
-You're lying.
-There is that possibility.
The truth.
My bull-riding career
was going down the drain.
-Okay, that's better.
-All right, now you.
(MAGGlE SlNGlNG
LOVE AND HAPPINESS)
I really should go.
Go? What? No, you're not going.
We're just starting to have fun.
You're insulting my drawing.
No, you were insulting your drawing.
Although, to be fair,
it's a pretty lame drawing.
All right. Well, you can't go,
'cause you owe me a dance.
No, I don't think so.
Well, then, I'm gonna
have to take that money back,
'cause I wouldn't feel right
taking the money...
Look, every 1 8 weeks,
a new bunch of you guys comes in,
all looking to score with the local talent.
I live here. I work here.
It's a good thing
I'm just asking for a dance, then.
Okay, one dance.
No attachments. Just casual.
I'm a guy. I can do casual.
Mmm-hmm.
I am the king of casual.
There's just one thing, though.
You're gonna have to stop
undressing me with your eyes,
'cause there's no way
you're getting me into bed.
Hey, you.
I gotta get to work.
-I'm late. I fell asleep.
-What...
-They're gonna kill me.
-They won't kill you.
This isn't like school.
They don't hand out tardies
in the military.
-You smell really good.
-I smell like you.
-He never came back?
-Nope.
Wow.
Four years as lead instructor,
I never had one go missing.
All right, take the others to the pool.
I'll catch up.
Aye, aye, Senior.
(DOOR OPENlNG)
(DOOR CLOSlNG)
(SKlNNER SlNGlNG)
(CADETS SlNGlNG)
Oh, God, there they are.
Stop. Stop the car. Stop.
-Here?
-Yes.
-Okay.
-I'll call you.
You better. Bye.
EMlLY: Jake! Jake! Jake!
SKlNNER: Airman Fischer's
coming in late, yeah
Here.
CADETS: Airman Fischer's
coming in late, yeah
Hi.
Must be nice to go out on a date, yeah
Oh, my goodness, look at this.
Look at this.
"Freshman Leads Team to State Title."
That's you.
Holy smokes.
"At only 1 6, Jake Fischer displays
the traits of a seasoned athlete.
"One thing's for sure: the future
looks bright for this young competitor."
Guess they didn't know
you were gonna flunk out of "A" School.
(LOCKER DOOR SLAMMlNG)
You have a nice evening?
Get dressed.
(CADETS GROANlNG)
Think we need another brick.
Bring it in.
Goldfish.
(CADETS GROANlNG)
Thanks to Mr. Fischer's
extracurricular activities,
you have all now gone 36 hours
without sleep.
Blow it.
Class leader, you are done.
Form it up in the shallow end.
Aye, Senior Chief!
Class 5506, form it up!
No. No, no, no. You're with me.
I'm a rescue swimmer, yes, I am
I'm here to pull your ass out of this jam
I jump from the helo
and swing from the cable
All right, knock it off.
I am having a hard time
figuring you out, Fischer.
I mean, you like seeing your picture
in the paper.
In it for the glory, maybe a few chicks.
Am I right?
But when it comes down to it,
you will choose yourself over them
every time,
Iike you did on the first day in the pool,
Iike you did yesterday
by missing muster.
Won't happen again, Senior Chief!
Why don't you do us both a big favor
and quit?
I'm a rescue swimmer, yes, I am
I'm here to pull your ass out of this jam
I jump from the helo
and swing from the cable
I'm not Tarzan
I'm just willing and able
Give me something else, Senior Chief.
CADETS: Thirty!
Thirty-one!
Thirty-two!
Thirty-three!
Thirty-four!
Thirty-five!
Thirty-six!
Stop. Drop them.
Senior Chief's on deck. Pop tall.
CADETS: Oorah!
Morning, class.
Today we were going to learn
about how to approach
a drowning victim in high seas,
but I think there are some here
who aren't interested in that victim.
Fact, I think there's some in this class
who aren't interested
in saving lives at all.
I believe there are some
who are more interested
in setting records.
So today is record day.
(BLACK REBEL MOTORCYCLE CLUB
PLAYING AlN'T NO EASY WAY)
5:28.
Put one on the board for Goldfish.
Wow, he's fast.
He's good.
You got it, man! You got it, Fisch!
Another record. Chalk it up, Chief.
-Get some.
-You are the man!
You people do not deserve
to be in the same pool as Jake.
He's destroying you.
Wow, look at him go! He's fast!
Wow, he's fast.
Come on, you're all fighting for second.
Just first loser.
This is fun.
We'll pass out trophies later.
Unbelievable.
You want me to pull these pansies out?
-You do not wanna hear about my day.
-Yeah, I do.
Man, this guy Randall...
You know, it doesn't matter what I do.
It's just not good enough.
Well, maybe he's just trying
to push you to be better.
You know, we teachers do that
to the ones we believe in.
No, it's personal with me.
He knows that I'm better than he was.
I mean, today,
I broke every one of his records.
I own them all.
Not all of them.
There's one record you won't break.
This is the Aegis.
Medical ship. Caught on fire.
It was a nightmare.
People burning in their beds.
And Ben Randall
got every one of those people off there,
except for this one guy.
And right when the ship
started to go down,
he reaches down and grabs this guy.
He's hanging from the cable
with this man's life in his hands,
and the winch jams.
It's 20 minutes to the base.
The man's screaming.
Ben looks him dead in the eye,
and you know what he said?
He said, "l won't let go."
What happened?
MAGGlE: Dislocated his shoulder,
tore every tendon in his hand.
But he didn't let go.
Twenty minutes, just fingertips.
You break that record
and you give me a call.
My day was all right.
(ABBY AHMAD PLAYING
TRl-ME)
So here's my thinking.
We should go on a date.
-Well, what do you call this?
-No, no, no.
I'm talking about, like, a real date.
You know, with, like, a nice restaurant,
some nice clothes.
I'll get you some flowers.
I thought we agreed
to keep this casual.
Look, it's one steak. What is...
One steak is not gonna forge some
kind of a lasting emotional bond.
I'm serious.
Yeah?
-Yeah.
-So am l.
It's one dinner. What's it gonna hurt?
Well, if you ordered a steak,
I'd imagine a cow would be involved.
What do you have, an art gallery
over here? What is this "2"?
It's so the guy behind me knows
what place he's coming in.
What about this one?
That is the initials of the guys
on my high school relay team.
A drunken celebration gone wrong?
Something like that.
-So, about this date.
-God. It's just dinner, right?
No flowers, where we will discuss
nothing emotional or important?
I am fully prepared
to do an entire hour
on nothing but the Chicago Bears.
And we can have
completely meaningless sex
immediately afterwards.
You think I'm gonna sleep with you
on our first date?
Think again.
(CHUCKLlNG)
You just head-butted me.
I'm gonna teach you the breaststroke.
It's pretty complicated,
different than that of the butterfly.
I guess I can't sleep.
Well, of course you can't.
Your wife left you.
Your best friend died.
You sound like a damn country song.
If you had a dog,
he'd be run over by now.
-So, did she send you papers?
-Yeah.
And did you read them?
No, I did not.
Well, you think you might ought to?
You know,
there never was anyone else, Mags.
Like hell, Ben.
You're a bigamist.
You been married to the Coast Guard
all along.
Give me that shoulder.
You probably swum it out of socket
trying to prove you're still 1 9.
Am I right?
When the heck did we get old?
Hell, I've always been old, Ben.
You know what, though? I don't mind.
I mean, if my muscles ache,
it's 'cause I've used them.
If it's hard for me
to walk up them steps now,
it's 'cause I walked up them every night
to lay next to a man who loved me.
I got a few wrinkles here and there,
but I've laid under thousands of skies
on sunny days, yeah.
I look and feel this way,
well, 'cause I drank and I smoked,
I lived and I loved,
and danced, sang, sweat
and screwed my way
through a pretty damned good life,
if you ask me.
Getting old ain't bad, Ben.
Getting old, that's earned.
BEN: There will come a time
when you might have to decide
who lives and dies out there.
It's a terrible responsibility,
but it is one you will have to make
as a rescue swimmer.
The bigger reality is,
it's also something
you're going to have to live with
as a human being.
There will come a time
when you're going to have to say no.
The most important person
to keep alive is yourself.
You'll be facing crews from five to 20,
all saying, "Save me, save me."
They're looking for a miracle.
-How old are you, Hodge?
-Twenty-four.
At 24 years old,
you have to become that miracle.
You have to find a way
to be that miracle.
Looking right,
looking center, looking left.
Oorah!
You okay, sir? I'm a rescue swimmer.
(GRUNTS)
Again.
(GASPlNG)
All right, that's it. Time-out.
-Panics every time, Senior.
-Hodge, over here.
Hey.
The only difference
between you and the victim
is the attitude
in which you enter the water.
You've gotta figure out
a way to be calm
in the face of chaos.
Do you understand?
That's your first challenge, Charlie.
One more and you're gone.
-Come out.
-Aye, aye, Senior Chief.
What's up, Big Fisch?
You don't have to take his shit, Hodge.
What do you know?
It's so easy for you, Fischer.
Is that right?
Yeah.
You know, you don't get it.
You don't realize
that you're tougher than I am.
And how's that?
Well, if I get kicked out of here,
I'm not coming back.
I'm definitely not coming back twice.
I mean, you got guts, man.
Stupidity.
How long you been here, man?
Altogether... I don't know,
1 0 weeks the first time,
-six weeks, two days the second time...
-Six weeks this time.
So basically, you've been here
Ionger than anybody
that's graduated this place,
but you don't think you can make it.
Lighten up on yourself, man.
Let's go. Let's get a beer.
Hey, wait. Don't you have a date
with the girl from the wedding?
Yeah, but it's not till 9:00.
We got time. Get dressed.
Let's go.
When you go under,
when you're pulling on your stroke,
-move your hand...
-Wait a minute. Where are we going?
Jake, that's a squid bar.
I mean, there's Navy guys everywhere.
I don't give a shit. A beer's a beer.
When you're pulling through the water,
you're gonna pull yourself through.
-Like, you know...
-So I'll go fast.
No, you wanna lay to your side
and pull it like that.
(COUNTRY MUSIC PLAYING)
Hey, Charlie,
you get those fittings replaced
-before you came off to get tanked up?
-Yes, sir, Captain.
Yeah, I'll believe that when I see it.
We go to "A" School,
which is the most difficult school
in the military.
The attrition rate's, like...
What is it, 50%?
50%.
-It's over 50%.
-Over 50.
We're still here,
'cause we're the best of the best.
When storms shut down entire ports,
you know who goes out?
We do.
When hurricanes...
When hurricanes ground the US Navy,
Iike these little guys over here,
guess who goes out?
That's right, we do.
Look, honey,
you better keep it down in here, okay?
Okay, honey. She called me "honey."
Okay, honey.
But when God himself reaches down
from heaven...
-What does he do, Jake, when he...
-Rips houses off the foundation.
When God himself rips houses
off the foundation, we go out,
because we are rescue swimmers,
and that is our job,
and that's what we do.
You might wanna
recheck your compass.
This ain't no puddle pirate bar.
No problem,
because we were just leaving anyway.
-Sit down, Hodge.
-Jake.
-Finish your beer.
Yeah, sit, Hodge.
HODGE: That's my beer, man.
Finished now?
Must be happy hour.
(GRUNTS)
(ALL SCREAMlNG)
(GLASS BREAKlNG)
Hey!
Back off.
Everyone in this place is retired Navy.
Hey. Hey, when do I get
that phone call?
I know I get a phone call.
When do I get my phone call?
Ma'am, I am sorry,
but if nobody come in 20 minutes,
I need the table.
-Okay.
-I'm sorry.
Yeah.
She's never gonna talk to me again.
You know they're gonna
kick us out for this, right?
Yep.
Least they can't say we quit.
I was never gonna make it, anyway.
Skinner's right. Panic every time.
Man, screw Skinner.
I'm Skinner. Break my hold.
Hey, what are you doing, man?
Come on, Fischer, get off me.
Clock's ticking. Break it.
Fischer, you're hurting me, man.
Fischer, get off me, man!
Come on, Fischer, you're hurting me.
Fischer, man, get off!
-Break the goddamn hold.
-Fischer, get off me, man!
-Break the goddamn hold, Hodge.
-Fischer, get off me!
I said, get off me!
All right.
Now, it's just like that
when you're in the water.
Well, now. We could come back.
Give you boys time for a smoke
and some pillow talk.
JAKE: You can't kick us out.
SKlNNER: It's called disorderly
conduct, and yes, we can.
-We didn't fail at nothing.
-Our profession is all about control.
You both failed miserably
in that department.
Hold it right there.
-Senior?
-Yeah, come in.
Their disenrollment records.
BEN: Bar fight?
-All right, bring them in.
-Senior.
Square it.
It's all my fault, Senior Chief.
Hodge had nothing to do with it.
-That true, Hodge?
-It's true.
All right. Fine, you're dismissed.
-Senior Chief, I was...
-I said that you are dismissed.
Let's go.
You're gonna kick me out
for defending the Coast Guard?
The Coast Guard's been around
for 200 years.
I doubt a couple of knuckleheads
like yourself are gonna defend it.
Sit down.
I've been trying to peel the layers
back on you for a while now, and l...
I just don't get it.
I mean, this kind of work
seems a little remedial
for someone like yourself.
You know, big swim champ,
offer to every lvy League.
You give it all up to be here with us.
-Why?
-I'm here to save lives, Senior Chief.
I spoke with your coach, Jake.
-You spoke with my coach?
-Yeah, I spoke with your coach.
Something in your file
just kept hanging me up.
You win the state championship
your freshman and sophomore year
and then you don't swim the next two.
I'm just a public school guy,
so pardon me,
but it didn't add up until now.
"Kirk Holloway,
1 00-meter medley winner,
"thrown through the passenger window.
"Pronounced dead at the scene.
"Abe lkeman, first team All-American,
lungs crushed.
"Carl Sandoval,
50-meter freestyle champ,
"made it all the way to the hospital.
Died of internal bleeding."
I guess you just know everything, then.
I know what it's like to lose a team.
Yeah?
What about living in a small town
where everyone thinks
that you killed their brother
or their son or their best friend?
You know about that?
Kind of small town where everyone
still waves to everyone,
just not to you?
I read the report, Jake.
Your blood alcohol was zip that night.
I'm guessing there was a flip
for designated driver.
You lost.
Guess that just makes it
all go away, huh?
No, it doesn't make it all right.
It just makes it an accident.
At least that's how it reads.
You were 1 6 years old, Jake.
I'm not your priest, but if I was, I think...
I think maybe you'd deserve a pass.
You're giving me a pass?
You just think you know everything
with your psychobabble bullshit.
Why am I here? Why are you here?
You're too old to be doing this.
You're washed-up here.
You don't wanna be teaching
a bunch of kids in a pool. Am I right?
I don't give a shit what you read
or who you talked to.
You don't know about me! You don't...
I have me under control.
I can see that.
The only difference
between you and me is,
I don't wear the ones I lost
on my arm, Jake.
I know where you're at, Jake.
I'm there myself.
I ask myself every day
why I was the one that survived.
-And?
-And...
And if I can't answer that for me,
I'm certainly not going to try
and answer it for you.
Have a seat.
I want you
to start being a member of this team,
the team you have now.
You have a gift, Jake.
You're the best swimmer
to come through this program,
hands down, by far.
You got a whole record board
to prove it.
But you know what I see
when I look at it?
I see someone fast enough
who's gonna get there first.
I see someone strong enough
who's gonna last.
I see someone who can save a life
that maybe nobody else could.
You really wanna honor
the initials on your arm?
Then honor your gift.
Save the ones you can, Jake.
The rest, we've gotta let go.
Does this mean
you're not gonna fail me?
For what, backing up a buddy in a bar?
Man, I got bigger problems than you.
I don't know about you,
but I could use a fucking drink.
Oops.
I'm gonna consider everything tonight
off-record and off-duty.
That was an invite.
Oh.
You gotta be kidding me.
-What was it they called you?
-"Puddle pirates," but it's not...
I'm way over it, Senior Chief. This is...
-Well, it's like sticks and stones.
-Well, we'll just have one beer.
(ROCK MUSIC PLAYING)
Great. They're angrier
and drunker. Perfect.
Hi. Two beers.
-You gotta be kidding me.
-That's what I said.
Look, I don't want any trouble, okay?
They really don't like us, do they?
No. They think they're better than us
because they're combat-oriented.
We're the Coast Guard, Jake.
Nobody really appreciates us
until they need us.
That him?
Yep.
So let me ask you a question
before we start bleeding.
All those saves...
What's your real number?
Do you have a death wish,
or are you just shit-stupid?
I'm gonna go with stupid this time.
-Hi.
Who's this, your old man?
You know,
I'm really glad you're still here.
-Oh, yeah?
-Yeah.
(GROANS)
-Behind you.
-Stand down! I said stand down.
I think you better leave.
Okay.
Come on, Jake.
All right, sit down. Have a beer.
-That went a lot better than I thought.
-Yeah.
-What the hell was that?
-I don't know.
Hey, I wanted to apologize to you
for what I said earlier about you
being old and washed-up now.
Is there anything
you'd like to say to me?
Like what?
I don't know, but I apologized to you.
I just thought that, you know,
there might be something
you've said or done
that you'd like to apologize to me for.
Why?
'Cause that's how it's done. I...
You suck at apologies, you know that?
I mean,
you're missing the whole concept.
(PHONE RlNGlNG)
-Hello?
-JAKE: Hi. It's me.
Are you okay? What happened?
I mean, I waited for two hours.
Yeah. No. Look, I'm really sorry. I...
What happened?
It's a really long story.
Let me just... Let me put it this way.
It was the best worst night of my life.
Well, I'm glad someone had fun.
Can I see you tomorrow night?
I have parent-teacher conferences
tomorrow.
What about the next night?
I have parent-teacher conferences
all week.
-You blowing me off?
-EMILY: No, Jake.
I wouldn't do that to somebody.
I gotta get up in a couple hours.
I gotta go.
-Yep.
-Goodbye.
BEN: All right, you know what
we briefed on the ground.
Same thing.
We're gonna stay together.
No matter what happens out there,
you stay together.
Whatever decision you make,
you make as a team.
We trained to freefall at 15 to 20 feet.
You fall from 50 feet,
it's like hitting concrete.
You fall 80 to 100 feet, you die.
CADET: Hey, where they going?
They're supposed to come back
for us, right?
I don't know.
Well, Hodge, you been here before.
They're gonna come back for us, right?
Yeah, but I never made it this far.
-You're kidding.
-Not to the final week.
They're not coming back.
-What do we do?
-All right, listen up.
We stay together as a group.
Nobody falls behind.
We all stay together.
One guy goes back,
we get him back up to the front, okay?
We're a team. Oorah.
-Oorah.
-Oorah!
Let's do it, 5506.
Sir, it's okay,
I'm with the US Coast Guard.
(GRUNTS)
BEN: Again.
I'm a Coast Guard rescue swimmer.
I'm here to help you.
(WHlSTLE BLOWS)
Time-out.
Class, pop tall.
Hodge, get yourself
to the side of the pool.
Aye, aye, Senior Chief.
CADETS: Oorah!
Easy, Chief.
Guess it was a lucky punch.
Hodge!
-You all right, Chief?
-You stay right there!
Well done, Charlie.
Well done.
Oorah, Chief Skinner.
Class 5506, "Oorah, Hodge," on three!
One, two, three.
CADETS: Oorah, Hodge!
Good for you.
Get their gear off.
-Go on, get that gear off.
-Get that gear off!
(lNSTRUCTORS SHOUTlNG
COMMANDS)
Get it off!
Class 5506,
will you come find me if I am lost?
CADETS: Yes, Senior Chief!
Will you come save me
if I am drowning?
Yes, Senior Chief!
I believe you would.
I have high hopes for this class.
I have high hopes for you.
Matthew Stokes, Savannah, Georgia.
MAN: Matthew, a job well done.
STOKES: Oorah, Captain.
Kenneth Weatherly,
Clearwater, Florida.
Go out there and do great things.
William Hodge, Astoria, Oregon.
Where's Senior Chief?
He had a chance to go back to Kodiak
and he took it.
He never had
much of a bedside manner.
He's a water dog, Jake,
and as it turns out,
not a half-bad teacher.
Best of luck.
Jacob Fischer, Kodiak, Alaska.
Congratulations, Jake.
Make us proud up there.
Aye, aye, Captain.
Scott Reeves, Sitka, Alaska.
Ladies and gentlemen, your graduates.
MAN: Oorah!
(PEOPLE CHEERlNG)
-Congratulations.
-Thanks a lot.
-Good job, guys.
-Good luck.
-Well, congratulations.
-Thank you.
It's okay.
We both knew
where this was going, right?
Just casual.
Right.
To getting what you've always wanted.
And always wanting more.
Take care of yourself, Jake.
-I gotta go to work.
-Yeah.
Bye.
HADLEY: Ladies and gentlemen,
welcome to the Rock.
I'm Captain William Hadley,
CO of Kodiak Air Station.
-Fischer.
-Yeah, right here.
Mr. Mitcheltree will square you away.
The rest of you,
step up here with Mr. Christiansen.
He will process you in.
(HELlCOPTER WHlRRlNG)
Oh, amazing.
Not only does he come back
in great shape,
but he still thinks he can cook.
-Hello, Jake. Welcome.
-How you doing?
-Good to see you again.
-You guys keep it warm here, huh?
Glad to know
you know where a free meal is.
We need three crews in Sitka
for the weekend.
You make sure that happens.
And the stand team arrives here
next Tuesday.
Patch things up with the wife?
You fix things up with that young lady?
Well, you still have a choice, you know.
Hey, there's a question
I wanted to ask you back in school
and I didn't.
But when you can't save them all,
how do you choose who lives?
It's probably different
for everybody, Jake.
Kind of simple for me, though. I just...
I take the first one I come to
or the weakest one in the group,
and then I swim
as fast and as hard as I can
for as long as I can.
And the sea takes the rest.
Think I'm ready?
I'm not your teacher anymore, Jake.
I'm just your fellow swimmer.
That's not exactly
the answer I'm looking for there.
If I did not think you were ready,
I would not put you in the Bering Sea.
FEMALE DISPATCHER:
6030, this is Kodiak Ops Cent.
We are diverting your training mission
at this time.
We have two young kayakers
swept into the cave
one mile south of Saltery Cove.
-How copy?
-PILO T 1 : 6030 copies.
-We're diverting at this time.
-We've got a real case now.
Okay, guys, that tide's coming in,
and we've got six- to eight-foot rollers
coming from the north.
Senior, what do you think
about taking Fischer with you on this?
I want him with me.
All right? He's good to go.
BEN: I don't think it's gonna be
a problem sliding in there.
I think the problem's gonna be
coming back out.
That's why I got Jake with me.
Got my human speedboat.
PILO T 2: Kodiak Ops, this is 6030.
We're on-scene at this time.
No sign of kayakers.
I'm taking her down.
Cabin door is open and locked.
PILOT 1 : Those are definitely
ten-foot waves.
Swimmer's coming to the door.
Remember, all right?
You got the whole weight of the ocean
punching through that opening.
You gotta read the hydraulics,
gotta count the waves,
then wait for the flush.
CREWMAN: Checking swimmer.
Sure as hell hope
you paid attention in class, Speedboat.
Swimmers in the water.
Swimmers okay.
Swimmer Two is making contact
with Swimmer One.
VlCTlM 1 : Hey!
Over here!
-Here.
-Over here!
Got them. Three o'clock.
Right here.
We're rescue swimmers.
We're gonna get you out of here.
VlCTlM 2: Can't believe
you guys actually got here.
Give me your hand.
JAKE: Just the two of you?
Yeah, yeah. His arm's hurt real bad.
All right.
Swimmer One. I got two survivors.
It's gonna be a basket pickup here.
BEN: Roger.
Broken here?
You take him first.
Get him in the basket.
I'll follow with the other one
right behind you.
-You got that?
-Yeah.
-You got it?
-Yeah, yeah.
All right. I'm gonna lower you down
in here, all right?
-Okay.
-Relax, buddy. I got you.
All right.
-You're with me.
-Okay.
I don't swim so good.
-You don't swim so good?
-No, sir.
It's okay. I swim pretty good.
All right, on your back.
-Wait. Are we gonna take the boat?
-I'm the boat.
Wait. Wait, wait, wait.
-I'm not ready! I can't...
-Hey!
-Wait, wait, wait...
-Settle down!
(THUDDlNG)
CREWMAN: Something's not right.
Swimmer One's going back
to the cave.
What happened?
He hit a log.
What? What are you...
What...
(GRUNTS)
-He's gone, Jake.
-JAKE: He's not.
(COUGHS)
He's just got a head laceration.
Here we go. Come on.
Let's go.
Let's go!
Senior Chief Randall! Lock it in.
It's simple physics.
We're just gonna time the flush,
all right?
All right.
You call it, Swimmer.
JAKE: Now!
Hey, I know you're tired, okay?
I know you feel tired right now.
But you need
to keep your eyes open, okay?
All right? All right?
Hey, I need you to keep talking to him.
-You keep talking to him.
-Okay.
Senior. Senior!
Can you open these up for me?
One by one,
I want you to hand them to me.
JAKE: Reyes!
He's fine.
Right here, buddy. Right here. Okay?
-Okay.
-Right here.
(WOMAN SOBBlNG)
-WOMAN: Robert!
-I'm okay.
He's got a compound fracture
in his right radius.
We tried to stabilize that a little bit.
We put a collar on this one,
but it's more precautionary
than anything.
Thank you.
This one's possibly
a little bit concussive.
We checked their vitals
the whole way back.
They're both mildly hypothermic,
but I think they'll come around.
Thank you so much.
You're welcome.
It happens, Ben.
Not to me. Not like that.
I want you to sign them in front of me.
Why don't you take some time
and think about it?
No. It's...
It's over. Just sign them.
Please.
Could've happened to anyone.
Maybe.
But what if it happens again?
What then?
Kid got a couple stitches.
He's gonna be fine.
We got him out of there.
No, you did.
You were strong out there today.
I was proud of you.
What are you gonna do?
Friend of mine once suggested fishing.
Think I might take his advice.
Fishing?
Yeah.
Guys like us don't go fishing.
Where have I heard that before?
Senior, before you go,
I gotta know one thing.
What's your real number?
Twenty-two.
Twenty-two?
That's not bad. It's not 200. It's not...
Twenty-two's the number of people
I lost, Jake.
Only number I kept track of.
Keeps the sea out of your mouth.
Hey.
Hi.
You started painting again?
Yeah. Great light up there.
You know,
I wanna apologize
for the phone calls, Helen.
I should've given you your space.
And you felt
showing up here unannounced
was the best way to communicate that?
Hey.
-Please just...
-Ben.
I want you to have it, along with these.
I signed them.
Why now?
I had a... I had a case a while back.
You know, a couple was drowning.
By the time I got there,
the husband
was dragging his wife under,
just trying to stay afloat.
Pure survival instinct.
It took me...
Took me a long time to understand
that that man was me.
(PAGER BEEPlNG)
Oh, man. Oh, doggone it.
Sorry.
Aren't you gonna answer that?
I'm not a rescue swimmer anymore,
Helen.
Bye, baby.
Lock it up.
We have a 75-foot fishing vessel
in distress,
taking on water in high seas.
She's dead in the water
with four souls onboard.
With its dewatering pumps
unable to keep up,
it's not a matter of
if this thing is going down, but when.
Tighten her down!
We gotta secure her.
(ALARM BEEPlNG)
BEN'S VOICE: There will come a time
when you're going to have to say no.
You'll be facing crews from five to 20,
all saying, "Save me, save me. "
They're looking for a miracle.
At 24 years old,
you have to find a way
to be that miracle.
PILO T: Sounds good. We'll plan
our free-fall deployment to the water.
-Are you good with that, Jake?
- Yeah, copy that.
Okay, if we have to put you in,
we're gonna get you in upswell
and let the waves
take you down to the boat.
-Are you good with that?
-Roger.
We're only gonna have
about 20 minutes on-scene,
-so we gotta be quick.
-Copy that.
All right, I got the vessel in sight.
Two o'clock, about 50 meters.
(MEN SHOUTlNG)
REYES: Cabin door open and locked.
Pre-rescue checklist
for free-fall deployment.
REYES: Whoa, whoa!
Boat just took a wave, sir.
One appears to have gone
on the edge.
He's hanging from the cargo net.
(SCREAMlNG)
We need to get our swimmer
down there.
PILOT: Computer's showing 60 knots...
Going off com.
Prepare for a free-fall deployment
of the rescue swimmer.
(SCREAMlNG)
Rescue checklist, part two.
Swimmer's getting ready.
Rescue checklist complete.
Swimmer's coming out.
Roger that. Check swimmer.
Swimmer's at the door, sir.
Checking swimmer.
Swimmer ready?
God help you if you ain't, boy.
Swimmer's away.
Swimmer's okay.
He's heading towards the vessel.
All right, he's cutting
through those waves pretty good.
That's it. He's approaching the vessel.
He's at the boat, sir.
(GRUNTlNG)
Man, are we glad to see you!
(MAN CHA TTERING
ON COAST GUARD RADIO)
PILOT ON RADIO:
Kodiak Ops, rescue 6034.
Fischer's onboard,
but vessel is compromised.
Taking on lots of water.
May not hold much longer.
Stand by for further.
How many guys you got on here?
Is anybody injured?
I got four guys.
This guy's got a broken leg.
The skipper's down below.
He's trying to start the pumps.
-All right, he's gonna go up first.
-All right.
PILOT 2: Kodiak Ops, Kodiak Ops,
this is rescue 6034.
There's three onboard with injuries,
one more down below.
What do you want me to do?
You there,
help me get him around in here.
-Bring him on in.
-All right.
(SCREAMS)
Basket is on its way up.
Strap in. Strap in!
The captain's down below,
and there's one other man on deck.
Help him out. Strap yourself in.
Get out of the way.
PILOT 1: I repeat, the boat's going
down fast. Eight minutes to bingo.
All right, come on, get in the basket.
REYES: I have
the ready-for-pickup signal.
Hold on.
PILOT 2: Swimmer One, Swimmer One,
come in.
Rescue swimmer, 6034.
Fischer. Come in, Fischer.
Swimmer One, Swimmer One,
come in.
-JAKE: This is Swimmer One.
-Roger that, Swimmer One. Go ahead.
JAKE: Swimmer One. I got one down
below. I'm gonna go down there.
Swimmer One, be advised
we've got seven minutes to bingo.
I'm going down.
-Captain?
-CAPTAlN: Yeah!
Captain?
(CAPTAlN GROANS)
Captain! I'm a rescue swimmer.
I'm here to help you out.
Your leg is jammed in here?
Or is it just closed...
It's the whole leg!
I tried to free the clutch and got stuck.
This is Swimmer One.
I got the captain down here
in the engine room. He's stuck.
We're gonna be a little bit.
Swimmer One, we're about out of time.
That boat's listing bad,
and we're two minutes to bingo.
I ain't leaving here without him.
Send somebody back for us,
'cause I'm staying down here with him.
Negative, Swimmer One.
We need you topside ASAP.
Swimmer One, 6034.
PILOT 2: Kodiak Ops, Kodiak Ops,
this is 6034.
Be advised we are RTB at this time.
We are leaving the rescue swimmer
on-scene.
I say again, we are leaving
our rescue swimmer on-scene.
Who do we have left in the shop?
08's all we've got left, sir, but no crew.
-All right, get her online.
-Yes, sir.
Lieutenant Krauss, suit up.
We're handling this.
I need a swimmer.
Don't worry.
No, no, they'll get him.
Don't worry! Don't worry.
(GROANlNG)
Here we go.
Hold on. Hold on.
-Ready to go home?
-Yeah, man.
Captain. Captain!
(GRUNTlNG)
-Are we cleared in, Lieutenant?
-KRAUSS: Aye, aye, Captain.
Outstanding.
Rescue Swimmer One, this is 6008.
Do you read?
Come in, Rescue Swimmer One.
6008. Do you read?
Come on, Jake, be there.
(JAKE GRUNTlNG)
(HELlCOPTER WHlRRlNG)
CREWMAN: Cabin door's coming
open. Cabin door's open and locked.
All right, right there.
Right side. Nobody onboard.
All right. I see what I want.
Just get me down.
The right-hand corner.
Try to avoid the rigging.
Okay, swimmer requests
aft right-hand corner.
Aft right-hand corner.
Okay, this is what we're gonna do.
Start a rescue checklist, part two,
for a harness deployment
of the rescue swimmer.
-No trail line...
-Roger that. Backup pump is on.
All right, we'll do the hoist at 1 00 feet.
Roger that.
KRA USS: Kodiak Ops, Kodiak Ops,
rescue 6028.
DISPA TCHER: Rescue 6028,
Kodiak Ops. Go ahead.
Swimmer's ready.
Load-checking swimmer.
And load check complete.
Swimmer's going out the door.
Swimmer's out the door.
Swimmer's on his way down.
Coast Guard helo, do you copy?
Coast Guard helo,
this is Rescue Swimmer One.
Do you copy?
CREWMAN: Forward, right 40.
Forward, right 30. Watch your altitude.
Roger.
(SCREAMS)
CREWMAN: Hold.
I have a fouled cable. Fouled cable.
Paying out slack.
Coast Guard helo,
this is Swimmer Number One!
I'm in the engine room,
and the hold of the boat is filling up!
-He's trying to free the cable.
-Come on.
Okay, cable free. Cable free.
Attaboy.
Cable's free,
and I got a fray right here.
It's still good. It's still good.
I can use it. It's all we got.
All right, good.
KRA USS: Go back and left, Captain.
Back and left. Roger that.
Jake.
Come on.
Jake!
Jake?
Senior? Senior, is that you?
Goldfish!
I checked all the locks on the door.
I can't get them loose. They're stuck.
No, no, I see the problem.
It's filling up, Senior Chief!
Senior Chief! Get me out of here!
I'm almost submerged!
You gotta get the door open!
Hold on, Jake.
(GASPlNG)
Senior! The captain's body!
We gotta let him go. Come on.
Jake, he's gone!
Jake!
I got both swimmers coming out.
-Both swimmers are in sight.
-All right, I got them.
Hook is going down.
Let's go forward, right 40.
Hook is halfway down.
I'm hooking into you.
We're only gonna get one shot at this.
I'm in.
I'm in!
I thought you were going fishing.
What do you call this?
(LAUGHS)
Whoa.
CREWMAN: The cable's starting
to part! The cable! Hold, hold, hold!
Okay, hold right there. Hold.
I'm bringing them up.
I gotta jam this cable into the drum.
What are you doing?
Don't even think about it.
It's not gonna hold us both.
What...
Yes, it will. Don't! It'll hold!
CREWMAN: Senior fell. Senior fell!
Jake's got him. Jake's got him.
I gotta get them up.
(GROANS)
I won't let go!
I know.
JAKE: Senior!
Senior!
Lower me down!
He just fell! He just fell!
Randall fell! Hit the water!
Lower me down!
He's in the water.
Been hit by a wave, full debris.
-Put me down!
-I can't!
You gotta lower me down now!
Get me out of here!
-You gotta lower me down!
-I can't!
I'll free-fall!
If I do, you don't come back.
I can't! I can't lose two!
Lost swimmer. Lost swimmer.
He saw the cable coming apart.
He just let go.
He was about 80, 90 feet up, sir.
He didn't come up. I don't see him.
Flash landing hover lights.
Monitor the radio, sir.
Look for flares, strobes, anything.
He fell right in the debris.
Lost swimmer. Lost swimmer.
JAKE: The Coast Guard conducted
one of the largest
search-and-rescue missions
for a single man in its history,
but the body of Senior Chief
Ben Randall was never found.
I'm sorry, Helen.
There's nothing more we can do.
(SOBBlNG)
JAKE: What makes a legend?
Is it what someone did
when they were alive...
HADLEY: Randall never was much
for this sort of thing.
JAKE:...or how they're remembered
after they're gone?
Some people actually believe
Senior Chief made the swim
to the Aleutian Islands.
He's standing
on a distant beach somewhere
with a fishing pole in his hand.
But I found my answer
a couple weeks later.
Where is he?
There's nobody else out there, man.
No, he was there.
He was with me the whole time.
He said he would hold on
till help arrived.
He never let go.
JAKE: There's a legend of a man
who lives beneath the sea.
He is a fisher of men,
a last hope for all those
who have been left behind.
He is known as the Guardian.
Ben Randall always said
life is about making choices.
In the end, by making his,
he helped me make mine.
What do you remember?
What did you smell?
What did you see?
How did this make you
feel?
I'll be right back.
What are you doing here?
I lied to you.
I can't do casual.
(BRYAN ADAMS PLAYING
NEVER LET GO)